Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *daf* is למד ב' *Lamed
Bet* and with today we will finish the third פרק perek *perek*
and as we will see we will turn onto the fourth פרק
perek. *perek* which is not just the next פרק perek *perek* but
it's sort of a category shift from issues we've been dealing with.
But anyway we pick up here at the top of למד ב'
עמוד א' aleph, *Lamed Bet Amud Aleph*
and it's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* two lines
from the top. We read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is focusing
completely on the אגדתא Aggadata *Aggadata* at the end of the משנה
Mishnah, *Mishna* about the importance of ברית מילה Brit Milah, *Brit Milah*
which it got into because of בנדר *be-neder* whether מולים *mulim* and
ערלים *arelim* refer the משנה mishna, *Mishna* says does not refer to
the physical reality of who has a ברית מילה Brit Milah *Brit
Milah* and who does not but it refers to Jews and non-Jews
respectively. So therefore it's really about a fundamental word that has come
to tie into identity of the Jewish identity and then the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* and then the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* continued with these אגדתות
*Aggadatas* about how important ברית מילה Brit Milah *Brit Milah* is. I
should mention that in addition to that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah. *Avodah Zarah* discusses this משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* in
the context of also that women are considered נימולים *nimmolim* Jewish women
from a perspective also about can a woman be a מוהל mohel
*mohel* or מוהלת *mohelet* I should say. So again but so again
not really about the physical reality as much as who is in
the ברית Brit *Brit* and who conceptually do we sort of you
know put into that category as being as an identity issue and
also והוי ארמי הוא *ve-havai Armai hu* exactly. And then just to
repeat also what we said yesterday the fascinating idea that this becomes
the focus of the end of this section of נדרים Nedarim *Nedarim*
that on the one of you know a thing that's all about
words creating reality and מילה Milah, *milah* on the one hand does
mean word as well so you know that's fascinating and with the
emphasis about how this is also about Jewish identity and there's no
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* as great as ברית מילה Brit Milah *Brit Milah*
and you know אברהם Avrohom *Avraham* was not whole until he had
the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* ברית מילה Brit Milah *Brit Milah* and all
this is about changing the physical reality of your body and in
that way very much in contrast to the phenomenon of נדרים *nedarim*
which changes identities of things through words as opposed to changing them
through actual physically you know making things different in the real world.
But of course then going back to the beginning of the משנה
*Mishna* where who is considered נימול *nimol* and who is considered ערל
*arel* is not just the physical reality it's also about at least
about the words we use and the categories we place things in
so this interesting dialectic between sort of you know the physical world
of איסור והיתר *issur ve-heter* and of things that create identity and
then the sort of conceptual world in which we live created through
our thoughts and our words which is the world of נדרים *nedarim*.
So I think it's a very interesting I don't think there's a
clear resolution here but I think it creates some very interesting tensions
and contrasts right at the end of these first three פרקים prakim
*perakim*. So we now continue with the אגדתא Aggadata. *Aggadata* we pick
up two lines from the top of למד ב' עמוד א' *Lamed
Bet Amud Aleph*. Let's just get read a little. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer* לא lo למשה רבנו ביקש
שטן להרגו *lo le-Moshe Rabbeinu bikesh Satan le-horgo* or some have the
גרסא girsa *girsa* אותו מלאך *oto malach*. It wasn't משה Moshe *Moshe*
whose life was at risk right because it said משה Moshe *Moshe*'s
life was at risk because he tarried
that he should not have sort of set them up in the
inn first he should have just grabbed the first opportunity to do
the ברית מילה Brit Milah *Brit Milah*. So it says no yes
that's what the problem was but it wasn't משה Moshe *Moshe* whose
life was at risk אלא לאותו תינוק *ella le-oto tinnok* שנאמר she'ne'emar
כי חתן דמים אתה לי *she-ne'emar ki chatan damim atah li* because
you are a bridegroom of blood. צא וראה מי קרוי חתן *tze
u-ree mi karui chatan* go see who is called a חתן *chatan*
הוי אומר זה התינוק *hevei omer zeh ha-tinnok* it must be the
infant. Now I have no idea how we get that I mean
if ציפורה Tzipporah *Tzipporah* is talking so I don't know her חתן
*chatan* is more her משה Moshe. *Moshe* than her son. The רא"ש
*Rosh* says I was looking the רא"ש *Rosh* says
why is he considered a חתן *chatan* so the רא"ש *Rosh* says
on the left-hand column he says שמחתנין אותו במצוה ראשונה *she-mitchatnin oto
be-mitzvah
rishonah*. I so I think he's trying to use that as a
word like מתחנכין *mitchanchin* like חינוך *chinuch* unless it means that you
are like marrying him you are creating his relationship to the world
of מצוות Mitzvos. *mitzvot*. The ר"ן Ran *Ran* says also I have
no idea I can't say ומה דחזינא *u-ma de-chazina* right מתחתנין *mitchatnin*
no it says מתחתנין
*mitchatnin* excuse me he doesn't say מתחנכין *mitchanchin* he says מתחתנין *mitchatnin*
right מתחתנין *mitchatnin* so like you marry him off or something to
the world of מצוות Mitzvos. *mitzvot*. Right the ר"ן Ran *Ran* says
שנעשה חתן על ידי ברית brit, *she-na'asah chatan al yedei brit*.
I have no idea what that means. So anyway so it's a
little bit of a circular argument. Oh of course the חתן *chatan*
must be the infant because an infant becomes a חתן *chatan* through
the ברית brit, *brit*. I like okay anyway I really so I
really don't get that but it is fascinating right is the idea
that he was at his life was at risk was that a
punishment or was that something about the very fact that somebody who
deserves a ברית מילה Brit Milah, *Brit Milah* doesn't have it you
know sort of makes them vulnerable and you know makes them not
let's say you know part of the Jewish nation or somehow outside
of the ברית Brit, *brit* etc. again. Obviously all very male here
that we're talking about, but I think it's interesting if it's about
the infant then it's not as much of a punishment as about
the importance of ברית מילה Brit Milah and the vulnerability without it
and what also should be mentioned here is
that in
the way we do a ברית מילה, Bris Milah the idea of
דם dam becomes very central in the ritual. I mean there's this
whole idea of first of all of הטפת דם ברית hatafat dam
brit for somebody who needs a ברית מילה Brit Milah. that does
not have a foreskin
and as people know right now about all the issues about מציצה
בפה metzitzah b'peh is very much a focus on a ritual deriving
from the idea of blood. There's even an idea that like if
there's a ברית מילה Brit Milah. on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah that
the בעל תוקע ba'al tokeiah and the בעל תוקע ba'al tokeiah is
the מוהל that he should not wipe his mouth clean from the
blood so that he should תוקע tokeiah the שופר shofar with the
blood of the ברית מילה Brit Milah on his lips so that
the blood of the ברית מילה Brit Milah comes together with the
קרבן korban of יצחק Yitzchak and so on and the reason I
mention that is because it starts tying into an idea of the
blood of sacrifices. And if you think about this that's like there
was this פרשה parshah here of ציפורה Tzipporah is very much a
פרשה parshah that emphasizes the blood and the blood as somehow somebody
who is susceptible to dying and the blood saves the person, saves
presumably the infant. And that obviously foreshadows also what's going to happen
in מצרים Mitzrayim that the blood of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
saves the people in the house that are vulnerable to this משחית.
mashchit. So here there's also some type of a thing that is
coming to destroy and the blood that is saving so the idea
of the blood of ברית מילה Brit Milah. as this salvific protective
type of a blood really exists only in this פרשה. parshah. Everywhere
else in the תורה Torah it doesn't talk about blood about ברית
מילה, Brit Milah. it just talks about removing the foreskin or talks
about the covenant. ביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו, bayom hashmini yimol b'sar
arlato, ימול לכם כל בשר. yimol lachem kol b'sar. The only sort
of talk about blood is here and that very much taps into
a world of קרבנות korbanot that could also be seen as a
type of a
substitute for child
sacrifice. So יצחק, Yitzchak, you have the ram and you have the
horn the שופר shofar thing I mentioned. So every child now what
you cut off a piece, you cut off the foreskin, every child,
every male child and then there's this blood so wanted just to
disturb you a little bit.
Yes, it's a mind very ethical issue so this infant was going
to be killed because of the laziness of a parent, of the
father basically. So this kid was going to... Yeah well that's true
that we know is a theology in the תורה Torah and in
the גמרא Gemara about the children suffering for the father as we
know it though right as we've seen.
But in terms of the contrast between נדרים and מילה, Milah, I
mean this is the
quintessential מצוה Mitzvah. that there's no intention on the person who is
obligated to have this.
Right so you're eight days old you have no... Yeah the מצוה
Mitzvah? is done to you you're not the one you mean so
it's very much the lack of consciousness as opposed to נדר neder
is all intention.
That's a nice point too, that's a very nice point too. Yes,
David you wanted to say something before? Okay so now we continue.
דרש darshed רבי יהודה בר ביזנא Rabbi Yehuda bar Bizna בשעה שנתרשל
b'sha'ah she'nitrashal משה
רבנו Moshe Rabbeinu
מן המילה min hamilah when משה רבנו Moshe Rabbeinu our master, no
longer משה הצדיק Moshe HaTzadik which he was in the משנה, when
משה רבנו Moshe Rabbeinu was tarried, was lazy, tarried regarding the ברית
מילה Brit Milah, בא אף וחמה
ובלעהו ba af v'cheimah uvela'uhu then these two destructive angels called אף
af and חמה, cheimah, anger and anger, I don't know what's the
other one, anger and rage, thank you, came, wrath and rage, came
and swallowed him up. Twin wrath and rage.
Yeah that's exactly that's ויבקש המיתו vayivakesh hamito is now being translated
in these like type of destructive forces. ולא
שיירו ממנו אלא רגליו v'lo shayru mimenu ela raglav and they only
the only part of his body they didn't swallow up was his
legs but the רן says this is a euphemism,
it means his penis.
אלא רגליו ela raglav מיד ותקח צפורה
צר miyad vatikkach Tzipporah tzor so ציפורה figured out what was going
on, she picked up on the hint so she took the rock
ותכרת את ערלת בנה vatikrot et orlat b'nah מיד miyad so immediately
as a response once she did the right thing וירף ממנו vayeiref
mimenu the angel, I mean it's in the singular, angels though, let
him loose, released him. באותה שעה ביקש b'otah sha bikesh משה רבנו
Moshe Rabbeinu להורגן lehorgan so משה Moshe wanted to now destroy these
two destructive angels, rage, wrath and rage שנאמר She-ne'emar, it says הרף
מאף
ועזוב חמה. heref me'af va'azov cheimah. So release אף af and abandon
חמה. cheimah. So there's this read like somebody wanted to seize them.
So this is read that משה Moshe wanted to seize them and
destroy them and get them rid of the world and God told
משה Moshe no actually this idea like divine anger is a necessary
part of the world.
Exactly. Wait, who'd they swallow up, the kids? No, in this it
says משה. Moshe
משה Moshe as an indicate? Right. ויש אומרים Ve-yesh omrim and some
say, some say, לחמה
הרג, Le-Cheima harag, משה Moshe actually did succeed in destroying one of
them, in destroying whichever, the worst one. שנאמר, Shene’emar, חמה אין לי.
Cheima ein li. I do not have חמה Cheima anymore.
Not just right now I don't have anger, but no, I don't
have it. משה Moshe. destroyed it. So, it
reminds us of the מדרשים Midrashim where it says in the time
of בית שני, Bayis Sheini, the אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesses Ha-Gedolah
got together and they wanted and they destroyed the
יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה. I think it's dealing with
the fact
that
it's the old question
of
why there are evil forces in the world, right? If God gave
us a good world, why are there evil forces in the world?
Like even if you just talk about why there are hurricanes, why
are there all these bad things? So, to some degree you have
some explanation that these are somehow
necessary. And therefore, the question is, they're necessary, but are they all
necessary? Does it have to be this bad or whatever? I think
that's sort of what the מדרש Midrash here is dealing with. We
understand to some degree that there's an idea of divine anger, but
maybe it's not appropriate and grappling with does it really have to
be as bad as it always is? So I think to some
degree that's what it's the question it's raising. Let's keep, let's read
a little bit more.
So it says, חמה אין לי, Cheima ein li, והכתיב כי יגורתי
מפני האף והחמה. Ve-hakativ ki agorti mipnei ha-af ve-ha-cheima. But משה Moshe
says but I was afraid, fearful from God because of the אף
Af and the חמה. Cheima. So
that's אף וחמה. Af ve-cheima. So he said that after, he said
that at the end of his career. So okay, תרי חמה הוו.
Trei Cheima havu. There are two types of חמה. Cheima. He got
rid of one but the other one was left. ואיבעית אימא Ve-iba'is
teima if you want, גונדתא דחמה. Gundat de-Cheima. That's talking about the
forces of חמה, Cheima, not חמה Cheima itself. So apparently, משה Moshe,
killed חמה Cheima but
he didn't kill the related forces that came with חמה, Cheima, the
after or something. I don't know what it means. Yes, Michael. I
was going to say that even the legs still could have meant
it literally, the meaning like it's supposed to be like ריצתא דבר
מצוה Ritzta de-bar mitzvah or like... Yeah, but then how did צפורה
Tziporah figure out what the problem was? No, I'm just saying that
could be the point. Like you didn't run to do a מצוה.
mitzvah Yeah, but what מצוה? mitzvah Had she just always clipped the
toenail? But what does it really mean though? Is there anything deeper
to say like he
could... he could have killed אף? Af? No, because they have a
פסוק Pasuk there that says חמה אין לי. Cheima ein li. No,
I understand, but I don't know, Michael, you can figure it out.
I told you what I know about this. Okay. ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'is
teima, okay we just did it. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא. Brayisa.
What? Well, that never tells us, never tells us that he circumcised
his other son either. It just tells us, I think we're supposed
to assume yes.
But the גמרא Gemara says
that
לוי Levi had always a tradition of being circumcised but בני ישראל,
Bnei Yisrael, the rest of בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael didn't. So משה
Moshe was part of לוי. Levi. But again, these things aren't explicit
in the פסוקים. Psukim. Well no, the assumption is he was, he
was part of לוי. Levi. Okay.
That's an interest to do with once circumcised. Well, that too. Right,
right, right. Okay. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Brayisa, רבי
אומר גדולה מילה שאין לך מי שנתעסק במצוות כאברהם אבינו. Rebbi omer
Gedolah milah she-ein lecha mi she-nitaseik be-mitzvos ke-Avrohom Avinu.
Now, back to the original command of מילה, Milah back to אברהם
Avrohom as opposed to משה. Moshe מילה Milah is great. By the
way, it is interesting thinking about these two models of משה and
אברהם Avrohom when we think about מילה mila, because the אברהם Avrohom
idea is much more the
Jewish identity
as an ethnic identity. I mean because אברהם Avrohom, is not yet
the one we identify with the תרי"ג מצוות, Taryag Mitzvos, right, with
our full religious obligations, right? אברהם, Avrohom everybody descends from אברהם Avraham
is part of the Jewish family. But it's not
yet Judaism, it's not yet like the identity of מצוות. Mitzvot. And
if you think about what בני יעקב Bnei Yaakov say to שכם,
Shechem, they say, כי לא נוכל לתת את אחותנו לאיש אשר לו
ערלה כי חרפה היא לנו, Ki lo nuchal laseis es achoseinu le-ish
asher lo orlah ki cherpah hi lanu, that it's very much about
like a type of an ethnic identity. So Jewish identity without yet
identifying with מצוות. mitzvot, Whereas by משה, it very much evokes
משה רבנו, Moshe Rabbeinu, the ברית and the aspect of the מצוות.
mitzvot. So just interesting thinking about them as different sort of models
when we think about ברית מילה Brit Milah and what identity and
symbolism it holds. Those models play out with גירות. Geirus. Right, absolutely.
So, it's a different story if everyone was circumcised but somehow this
משה's son hadn't been circumcised yet or somehow wasn't circumcised. And somehow
without being told or commanded, משה's wife figured it out. I don't
think she figured anything out. I think
that... Right, right, right, which means she figured it out. I mean
I’m not saying she figured it out because of these angels, somehow
she intuited it or something. Maybe she tried ten other things and
this was the one that worked.
Cut him here, that didn’t work. Cut him here, that didn’t work.
Oh well this actually works. Okay.
Alright, תניא. Tanya. Okay,
רבי אמר Rabbi amar גדולה מילה שאין לך מי שנתעסק במצוות. gedola
mila she’ein lach mi shenit’asek bemitzvot. Although ironically, although I just said
that אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu sort of symbolizes, you know, an identity
issue and, you know, a family, an ethnic identity issue, here the
focus is about this as מצוות, mitzvot right? And that this is
the prime מצווה. mitzvah. So שאין לך מי שנתעסק במצוות כאברהם אבינו.
she’ein lach mi shenit’asek bemitzvot ke’Avraham Avinu. Right, nobody was as great
in מצוות. mitzvot Very interesting, right? Because this is מצוות mitzvot before
they were commanded. Right, it means like nobody was as sort of
as much like alacrity and zealousness in terms of like doing everything
God wanted. Like this drive to serve God, but it’s still מצוות
mitzvot not in the sort of technical commanded sense. I mean he
was told to go to ארץ כנען, Eretz Kna’an, but still נתעסק
במצוות, nit’asek bemitzvot, right, יותר כאברהם אבינו, yoter ke’Avraham Avinu, ולא נקרא
תמים, velo nikra tamim, he wasn’t called whole, full, complete, אלא על
שם מילה ela al shem mila only because of the ברית מילה.
brit milah, שנאמר, Shene’emar, התהלך לפני והיה תמים. Hithalech lefanai vehye tamim.
Walk before me and be complete. And then the next verse is,
right, ואתנה בריתי ביני ובינך, Ve’etna briti beini uveinecha, and then God
commands him on the ברית מילה. brit milah וכתיב Uchtiv ואתנה בריתי
ביני ובינך. ve’etna briti beini uveinecha. Okay, so you see that this
is really that no matter how many מצוות mitzvot a person does,
this is the one that makes, at least again speaking for men,
makes him complete. דבר אחר, Davar acher, another explanation, גדולה מילה ששקולה
כנגד כל המצוות. gedola mila sheshkula keneged kol hamitzvot.
It’s of equal weight of all the other מצוות שבתורה. shebaTorah. שנאמר,
Shene’emar, כי על פי הדברים האלה כרתי אתך ברית ואת ישראל. ki
al pi hadevarim ha’ele karati itcha brit ve’et Yisrael. Because of these
things I have made a covenant. So all the מצוות are part
of a ברית, and ברית מילה brit milah, is a ברית, so
therefore it is equal to all of those other things. Written in
a time when the Jews were resisting circumcision during all these struggles.
Right, clearly. I mean certainly in the
Hellenist period, right, they were, the Greeks sort of thought that ברית
מילה brit milah was a disfiguring of the body and there was
a pressure to not mutilation of the body, not doing it, and
we actually know that a lot of Jews actually reversed it. Right,
exactly. So, yes, it was very much about making a statement about
are you part of the Jewish people or not part of the
Jewish people. In the Greek and Roman practice in the gymnasium where
they would compete in athletics in the nude, but they needed to
have a foreskin so they reversed it. Exactly. Exactly. דבר אחר, Davar
acher, גדולה מילה שאלמלא מילה לא נתקיימו שמים וארץ. gedola mila she’ilmalei
mila lo nitkaymu shamayim va’aretz. Were it not for מילה, Milah heavens
and earth would not be sustained. שנאמר, Shene’emar, אם לא בריתי יומם
ולילה חוקות שמים וארץ לא שמתי. im lo briti yomam valayla chukot
shamayim va’aretz lo samti. So if not for my covenant. So often
this verse is read as referring to תורה, Torah, you know, and
to the learning of תורה Torah that keeps the world spinning and
here it's learned about ברית מילה. bris milah So that’s quite fascinating,
right? It’s not just about a person’s identity and wholeness, תמים. tamim.
It’s not just about its
power in מצווה, mitzvah, it’s שקולה כנגד כל המצוות, shkula keneged kol
hamitzvot, but actually its metaphysical power is that it very much like
keeps the entire world sustained. ופליגא דרבי אליעזר, Upliga deRabbi Eliezer, and
it argues with Rabbi Eliezer. דאמר רבי אליעזר De’amar Rabbi Eliezer גדולה
תורה שאלמלא תורה לא נתקיימו שמים וארץ. gedola Torah she’ilmalei Torah lo
nitkaymu shamayim va’aretz. שנאמר, shene'emar, אם לא בריתי יומם ולילה חוקות שמים
וארץ לא שמתי. im lo briti yomam valayla chukot shamayim va’aretz lo
samti. It’s about תורה, Torah, not about ברית מילה. bris milah Which
is by the way also very fascinating because, you know,
it’s also one could sort of see this as a, you know,
תורה Torah is a... that statement that תורה Torah keeps the world
going feeds into a certain also type. I mean on the one
hand, it’s yeah, the power of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah which has
sustained the Jewish people as the people of the book and so
on. On the other hand, it also it does feed into a
little bit of an elitism, right? Because how many people devote themselves
to the learning of תורה? Torah? Right? I mean now we are
living in a golden
age where so many people do the דף יומי Daf Yomi and
it’s so widespread or whatever, but anyway historically only a very tiny
percentage of the people could really sort of say that. So if
it’s תורה Torah keeps the world going, then it’s the תלמידי חכמים
Talmidei Chachamim keep the world going. If it’s ברית מילה, bris milah
you know, okay, it sort of excludes 50% of the population, but
at least it fully includes the other 50%, you know, so there’s
a different sort of emphasis there as well in terms of it’s
a big difference in terms of sort of a populist or an
elitist type of an approach.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says. It distinguishes again,
yeah, this passive versus active so. That too, yeah. So now are
you, do you do something with your actions or do you effect
change even if
you have nothing to do with the decision to cause an action?
Right, you’re just who you are is significant, just the fact that
even if you’re not doing anything, it’s just part of your body.
Right, that’s all correct. And I think that there, I think it
minimizes the importance of ברית מילה bris milah, by. Making it something
that you don't really do on your own, that it's done on
your behalf for you by someone else. Right. Right. So I mean
not minimize in a negative way, but just it's a statement about
the fact that sometimes the most important things are not in your
control. That's a nice very nice point. Right. Okay, well said. Alright,
so now the גמרא Gemara says next point. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב בשעה שאמר הקדוש ברוך הוא לאברהם אבינו התהלך לפניי והיה תמים,
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: Besha'at she'amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu l'Avraham Avinu:
'Hithalech lefanai veheye tamim', אחזתו רעדה, ahazato ra'ada, he was seized with
trembling. אמר שמא יש בי דבר מגונה? Amar: Shema yesh bi davar
meguneh? Why is God saying become whole and complete? Is there perhaps
in me something that is disgusting, that you know,
unseemly, that I have now to now correct about myself that I'm
not yet whole and complete? כיון שאמר לו ואתנה בריתי ביני ובינך,
Keivan she'amar lo: 'Ve'etna briti beini uveinecha', then God said no, no,
here's what I mean, I mean that you have to do a
ברית מילה, Brit Milah נתקררה דעתו, nitkarrera da'ato, so that he got
cooled down because he basically realized, oh, it's not like my character's
incomplete, you know, it's something about my physical body and it's a
מצוה mitzvah that God has not yet commanded me. ויצא אתו החוצה,
Vayotze oto hachutza, now we are interestingly I have no idea what
this has to do with the ברית מילה Brit Milah discussion other
than where God and
אברהם Avraham, discussions. Okay, so God took him outdoors. ויצא אתו החוצה,
Vayotze oto hachutza, this happened before the מצוה mitzvah, of ברית מילה,
Brit Milah. this is two פרקים prakim earlier. Okay, and there's a
tradition that אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu knew all the מצות, mitzvot, he
intuited them. Right. Right. I mean when it says נתעסק במצות, nit'assek
bemitzvot, I'm not exactly sure that's the same tradition as he was
מקיים כל התורה כלה, mekayem kol hatorah kullah, it could just mean
like his alacrity in doing, you know, serving God and doing everything
that God had asked. But anyway, but ויצא אתו החוצה, Vayotze oto
hachutza, we are now just talking about God and אברהם, Avraham not
exactly... we've left the ברית מילה Brit Milah. discussion. אמר לפניו, Amar
lefanav, אברהם Avraham said to God, רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam,
נסתכלתי במזל שלי, nistakalti bemazal sheli, I looked in my, you know,
my astronomical sign, and this גרסא girsa says אין לי אלא בן
אחד, ein li ela ben echad, I only have one son, which
does not make sense because this פרק perek, happens before ישמעאל Yishmael
was born, so the side גרסא is ואיני ראוי להוליד בן, ve'eini
ra'ui l'holid ben, and I don't have the ability to have children,
right, which we knew, I mean אברהם Avraham, was already how old
was he, 90 years old or something, he didn't have any children.
So אמר לו, amar lo, so God said to him, or at
least at that time he might have been 75, whatever he was,
אמר לו, amar lo, so God said to him, but he didn't
have kids till 90, צא מאצטגנינות שלך, Tze meistagninus shelcha, leave your
astrology, אין מזל
לישראל, ein mazal l'yisrael, you know there is no מזל, mazal, the
force of the astrological, you know, constellations they
have no force on the Jewish people, we are למעלה מן המזל.
lemala min hamazal. Now I think that what I would suggest is
going on here, right? And רש"י Rashi quotes this on the תורה,
Torah, and רש"י Rashi ends by saying, it might be in the
מדרש רבה, Midrash Rabbah, אברם אינו מוליד אברהם מוליד, Avram eino molid,
Avraham molid, right? אברם Avram doesn't have children, won't have children, that's
what you see in your מזל, mazal, but אברהם, Avraham, when your
name changes, then you will have children. Now that is
like your, 'oh that's a loophole,' but I think it's more than
that, and I think what I would say this is doing here
in the discussion of ברית מילה Brit Milah, is the idea, right?
I mean this is also sort of why the Greeks criticized it,
like you know they said it was a disfiguring of the body.
God gives you the body, the body is perfect. What are you
doing mutilating what God has given you? Right, and I think that
the message here is, is that like you know there's the natural
order of things, like the מזל, mazal, you know, if I mean
for us we you know can't relate to the idea of מזלות,
mazalot, but we could sort of say the forces of nature which
would dictate a particular way in which things would occur and then
actually God, the commandment of the ברית מילה brit milah. is we
sometimes have to like you know break away from that, you know
it doesn't we're not subservient to the forces of nature, we can
actually change things, rise above that, change the course of the way
things are going. So that's אין מזל לישראל, ein mazal l'yisrael, so
you do the ברית מילה brit milah, and also that's where his
name goes from אברם Avram to אברהם, Avraham. right in that same
פרשה parsha where God gives him the מצוה ברית מילה, brit milah,
God gives him that extra ה heh in the אברהם. Avraham So
I think that that is the point. You are transformed, you change
yourself, you rise above the natural forces of the universe, the natural
forces of nature. So that's what I how I do think that
this is very related to the previous discussion.
Profoundly empowering of human beings. Yeah, yeah. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi
Yitzchak, so רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak said: כל המתמים עצמו הקדוש ברוך
הוא מתמים עמו. Kol hamatmim atzmo hakadosh baruch hu matmim imo. So
this is היה תמים heye tamim be perfect, but also be like
innocent, you know like anybody who makes himself like deals with integrity
let's say with himself, you know God deals, you know God deals
with integrity with him. How do they translate מתמים matmim there? They
say wholehearted. Wholehearted. All right. Wholehearted way with God. Okay, שנאמר, Shene'emar,
as it says: עם חסיד תתחסד, im chasid titchasad, with the righteous
you God will deal
righteously, עם גבור תמים, im gibbor tamim, and with a the the
whole the... hero, תתמם, Titamam, you will deal, you know, with integrity.
Or what do you say they said there? Wholeheartedly. So the one
who is strong in his wholeheartedness, you would deal wholeheartedly. Okay. אמר
רבי הושעיא, Amar Rabbi Oshaya, כל המתמים עצמו שעה עומדת לו. kol
hamatmim atzmo sha'ah omedet lo. If you make yourself תמים, tamim, then
the, you know, you'll have, you'll be very successful. That's an idiom
to mean you'll have great success. שנאמר, Shene'emar, התהלך לפניי והיה תמים,
Hithalech lefanai veheyeh tamim, וכתיב, u'chtiv, והיית לאב המון גויים. vehayita l'av
hamon goyim. If you will be תמים. tamim. And
by the way, I do want to say, a subtle thing has
just occurred here because we've been talking about how great ברית מילה
brit milah, and it's sort of similar to the tension I suggested
in the first
משנה, right? נדר Neder which is your words and ברית מילה brit
milah. which is your physical body. We go from the פסוקים psukim
that nothing is as great as ברית מילה. Brit milah אברהם Avraham
did not become whole and complete until he made this physical change
in his body, until he did ברית מילה. Brit milah And now
we’re saying, בי תמים, bei tamim, it's about a character trait, right?
It's not about have a ברית מילה, Brit milah, it's about, no,
the message is how do you become, you know, complete, integrity, wholehearted,
pure, and that's the goal. And if, you know, that's what you
do, then you will be, have this reward. But wait, wouldn't one
flow from the, in other words, it's an external-internal? Correct.
Correct, but it's, but it's like, you know, but that's a חידוש,
chiddush, right? Okay. אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi, says Rabbi, or רבי לוי,
Rabbi Levi, כל המנחש, kol hamenachesh, so here's the opposite of being
תמים. tamim. תמים Tamim is just like, you know, having like pure
faith in God, not sort of trying to beat the system or
like,
so you know, like just, just faith. So the opposite of that
is כל המנחש, kol hamenachesh, which is somebody who is trying to
like use divination, thank you, you know, figure out the future, not
because, you know, they don't have faith, they're so, they have to
try to use all these devices, these magical devices to figure out
what things are, what's going to be in the future. So כל
המנחש, kol hamenachesh, anybody who does this, לו נחש, lo nachash, that
person will get snakes going after him. Okay, it's just going to
come back to bite you. Oh, you like that pun? Back to
bite you. Okay, שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says, כי לא נחש ביעקב,
Ki lo nachash b'Yaakov, because לו lo read with a ו, vav,
to him is נחש ביעקב. nachash b'Yaakov. והא בלא למד אלף כתיב,
V'ha b'lo lamed aleph ktiv,
but it says לא with a ל lamed א, which means there
is no נחש nachash in יעקב. Yaakov. אלא משום מידה כנגד מידה.
Ela mishum mida k'neged mida. Fine, it's not based on a פסוק,
pasuk, it's just based on measure for measure. You know, you try
to go ahead, if you try to go ahead and like divine
and cheat the system or figure things out, don't have that simple
faith, then in the end, it'll actually come back, as I said,
to bite you. Whatever, anyway, you'll come back and suffer as a
result. The best is, don't have anxiety of the future, just have
faith in God. עם חסיד תתחסד עם גבור תמים. Im chasid titchasad
im gibor tamim. Right, exactly. Exactly. תני אהבה בריה דרבי זירא, Tani
Ahava brei d'Rabbi Zeira, or אהבה Ahava the son of רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira taught, כל אדם שאינו מנחש, kol adam she'eino menachesh, if
you do not try to have divination,
מכניסין אותו במחיצה, machnisin oto b'mechitza, he's brought into the inner chamber,
right, שאפילו מלאכי השרת, she'afilu malachei hasharet, that even the heavenly angels,
אין יכולים ליכנס בתוכה, ein yecholim likanes betochah, are not allowed in.
You get to be super close to God. שנאמר, Shene'emar, כי לא
נחש ביעקב, ki lo nachash b'Yaakov, there's no divination in יעקב, Yaakov,
ולא קסם בישראל, v'lo kesem b'Yisrael, and there is no witchcraft or
whatever in ישראל. Yisrael. And the end of the פסוק pasuk is
כעת יאמר ליעקב ולישראל מה פעל אל. Ka'et ye'amer l'Yaakov u'lYisrael mah
pa'al El. Now it will be told to יעקב Yaakov and ישראל
Yisrael what God is doing, what God has done. So if you
are have, you know, full faith in God and how God acts
in the world and what God will do in the world, right,
so then you will know better than the angels what God is
going to do. And if you try to figure out, actively figure
out what God is going to do through your נחש, nachash, right,
then you'll lose out. But if you just have faith, you'll even
be at a higher level than the angels and you will, you
know, you won't have to worry about the future. אמר רבי אבהו
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Elazar, מפני מה נענש
אברהם אבינו ונשתעבדו בניו למצרים? Mipnei mah ne'enash Avraham Avinu venishtabdu banav
l'Mitzrayim? Why was אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu punished and his children were
enslaved in Egypt מאתיים ועשר שנים, matayim ve'eser shanim, 210 years? מפני
שעשה אנגריה בתלמידי חכמים. Mipnei she'asah angarya b'talmidei chachamim. So this seems
to be coming out of nowhere, because he basically drafted Torah students.
You can imagine that this גמרא Gemara is—not just imagine, I will
tell you—this גמרא Gemara. is quoted a great deal
among in the חרדי Charedi community, in the ישיבה Yeshiva community in
ישראל Yisrael about why they don't have to serve in the army.
Because אברהם Avraham drafted תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim to serve in his
army, that's why the children were enslaved in Egypt. How do you
know he did that? שנאמר, she'ne'emar וירק את חניכיו ילידי ביתו, Vayarek
et chanichav yelidei beito, he armed his, you know, his trainees, those
who are in, from his
household. And who are ילידי ביתו? yelidei beito? So it's understanding that
that somehow refers to the תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. I'm trying to
remember why it's assumed to refer to that.
Oh, because it's just the word from חניך, chanich, the ר"ן says,
לחנך בתורה, l'chanech ba'Torah, those that have been initiated into the Torah.
Anyway, somehow it's understood. Where'd they study? Well, the תורה Torah of
שם ועבר. Shem v'Ever. I mean, that's where יעקב Yaakov went to
the ישיבה yeshiva of שם ועבר, Shem v'Ever, right? All the תורה
Torah they inherited from נח. Noach. Anyway, all right, so that's how
it's understood, that that's why he was punished. רב אמר Rav amar
אנגריא. Angaria.
אנגריא Angaria is like a draft. A draft? Yeah. And how do
you know that he was punished because of that though? Because the
גמרא Gemara? is telling you. Okay. I don't know. ושמואל אמר מפני
U'Shmuel amar mipnei
Shmuel says a more direct reason in the פסוקים pesukim שהפריז על
מדותיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא. shehifriz al middosav shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu.
He was a little bit too... too חוצפהדיק, chutzpadik, you know, regarding
God's attributes, we'll see what this means. שנאמר: במה אדע כי אירשנה?
shene'emar: Bama eida ki irashena? What's with what will I know that
I will inherit the land of Israel? So rather than just having
faith in God's promise, he pushed God a little bit too far.
So I think that if you ask what is this doing here
other than it's another discussion between אברהם Avraham, and God, I would
say it's in contrast to the תמים tamim point before. The תמים
tamim point before was have faith, things will work out, certainly if
God explicitly promises you something, don't say במה אדע, Bama eida, how
am I going to know? Right? That's the whole idea of no,
you know, you're supposed to have faith in God. So here אברהם,
Avraham the one time he didn't do that and he said במה
אדע, Bama eida, this is how, you know, he was punished. I
think the issue about the drafting the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim is
just a digression, like it's just, I think the point here of
the tie-in is the second statement. I don't know how to bring
the drafting of the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim into the larger theme
of what we're discussing. Yes. I just want to suggest something. I
can't prove this from the text, but we keep on saying you
should have faith as an way of understanding תמים. tamim. תמים, tamim,
I just want to say, to me have faith is kind of
a cognitive idea. Like it's what I think, right? I believe like
I... No, have faith in God. I don't mean תמים tamim is
like he's just sort of flows... Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's what I
mean. Naivety in a way. Well, no, but okay, but I would
still say faith, but that's what I mean. I mean I don't
mean like dogma and a belief, I believe that. Having faith in
God is not to believe... Trust, have trust, have trust in God.
Have trust in God. Right. It's experience.
Yeah, totally. It's exactly what I meant.
Okay.
רבי יוחנן אמר: שהפריש בני אדם מלהיכנס תחת כנפי השכינה. Rabbi Yochanan
amar: shehifrish bnei adam milhikaneis tachas kanfei haShechina. No, the problem was
was that he actually had people that he could have brought under
the divine wings, you know, into the community of faith, that's anyway
under God's, you know, under God, and he lost the opportunity. He
separated them out. שנאמר: תן לי הנפש והרכוש קח לך. shene'emar: Ten
li hanefesh veharchush kach lach. That מלך סדום Melech Sedom says to
אברם: Avram: Give me the souls, the people that you recaptured, and
you can take the booty.
And אברם Avram says I don't want the booty, but he should
have said I don't want the booty, I want the souls. He
had an opportunity to bring these people, you know, into his community
and to serve God. And he lost them. In other words, he
refused... He should have offered him the reverse is what it's basically
saying. אברהם Avraham, refused everything, right? He says I don't even want
the money. But the מדרש Midrash says what do you mean? You
had an opportunity to just to keep the people and you could
have brought them to serve God. Okay. So, right. Okay. וירק את
חניכיו ילידי ביתו. Wayyarek es chanichav yelidei beiso. By the way, so
talking about how גמרא אגדתא Gemara Agadata can be used for different
people's types of agendas, the same way you could use the or
whatever, religious viewpoints, the same way you could use the first part
to say, you know, ישיבה yeshiva students shouldn't be drafted, you could
use the last part to say why we have to have a
much more proactive approach towards גירות, geirus, you know, and you have
a million Russian עולים olim that are that are halachically, you know,
not Jewish because nobody has done anything about it and has these
very high impossible standards in terms of conversion. So look at what
happened with אברהם, Avraham just three hundred people he could have brought
close to God. These things he says, in other words, when you
know when people are saying, alright, there's a lot of different aggadic
statements, you know, I mean there's so many, you know, it's like
devil quoting scripture, there's so many different voices, right? You can quote
the ones that support your agenda. So I mean okay anyway so
okay. רב אמר Rav amar what? Devil quoting scripture. Yeah. Okay. Anyway.
So וירק את
חניכיו ילידי ביתו. Wayyarek es chanichav yelidei beiso.
Now that we're dealing with this story about him arming his, you
know, those in his household to run after לוט. Lot. So now
we're going to talk about this a little bit. רב אמר שהוריקן,
Rav amar shoherikan, וירק Wayyarek which in the פשט pshat means like
he he armed them. It says שהוריקן בתורה. shoherikan b'Torah. That basically
he... so some say שהוריקן מהתורה, shoherikan mi'haTorah, consistent with the earlier
reading that he took them out of the ישיבה, yeshiva, so להוריק
lehoreik means he emptied them from תורה Torah of תורה. Torah. Or
it could just mean he initiated them in תורה, Torah, okay, that's
but anyway two ways of reading that, whether it's בתורה biTorah or
מהתורה. miTorah. ושמואל אמר שהוריקן בזהב. u'Shmuel amar shoherikan bezahav. He...
because the word ירוק yarok like green but it also means like
green-yellow. Yellow. So he like, you know, he gilded them with gold.
I don't know it's going to be hard to run after the...
Gold is heavy. Oh maybe. Oh that's a nice point. Yeah, you're
probably right. שמנה עשר ושלש מאות. Shmona asar ushlosh me'os. So three
hundred eighteen. אמר רבי אמי בר אבא: אליעזר כנגד כולם. Amar Rabbi
Ammi bar Abba: Eliezer kineged kulam. אליעזר Eliezer was equivalent to all
those three hundred eighteen in terms of the ability to wage war.
wage war against these armies. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say אליעזר
הוא. Eliezer hu. No, no, no, 318 didn't literally mean 318. It
wasn't 318 people that came with Avraham, it was just Eliezer. How
do we know Eliezer, where does Eliezer fitting into this whole thing?
דחושבניה הכי הוה d'hushbanei hachi hava because the gematria of 318 is
the same gematria of Eliezer. Okay, you can see it, right? Cause
the
resh is 300, the lamed and the ayin is 70 and 30
is another 100, and then the yud zayin aleph is 18, 318.
So Eliezer is the 318 or he was equal to the 318.
ואמר רבי אמי בר אבא, V'amar Rabbi Ami Bar Abba, בן ג'
שנים, ben gimel shanim, now that we're dealing with אגדתא with Avraham,
בן ג' שנים הכיר אברהם את בוראו. ben gimel shanim hikir Avraham
et boro. Avraham recognized God at the age of three, שנאמר Shenemar,
as it says עקב אשר שמע אברהם בקולי Ekev asher shama Avraham
b'koli because Avraham heard my voice, חושבניה מאה ושבעים ותרי. hushbanei me'ah
v'shiv'im u'trei. So the gematria of עקב Ekev is 172. And Avraham
lived to 175. So Avraham listened to my voice for 172 of
his years. So he recognized me at the age of three. Okay,
but it's interesting debate of רמב"ם Rambam and ראב"ד Ra'avad when רמב"ם
Rambam sort of in the beginning of משנה תורה Mishneh Torah describes
how Avraham comes to know God, he has Avraham sort of philosophically
coming to an understanding of God and he says Avraham sort of
you know became aware of God at the age of 40.
And then the ראב"ד Ra'avad quotes this גמרא Gemara and says no,
he became aware of God at the age of three because ראב"ד
Ra'avad was more of like a mystic and a kabbalist so you
know he could accept the idea that even a three-year-old could somehow
intuit or know God, where for רמב"ם Rambam knowing God means intellectually
knowing God and therefore takes a different אגדתא. רמב"ם Rambam just discounts
this kind of גמרא. Gemara Well there are different גמרות, Gemaras, yeah.
He said 40 for Avraham. Where's
there another גמרא? Gemara There's a מדרש Midrash that says 40. 40,
yeah, not here. I don't know what the other sources are, it's
a מדרש Midrash somewhere. So Avraham quotes that because Avraham talks about
Avraham coming to a philosophical intellectual knowing of God.
And ראב"ד Ra'avad quotes this. Who quotes that? רמב"ם, Rambam, רמב"ם. Rambam.
Yeah, okay. It's also עקיבא Akiva 40. Yes, right, exactly. ואמר רבי
אמי בר אבא V'amar Rabbi Ami Bar Abba and Rami Bar Abba
also said השטן HaSatan
so the word השטן HaSatan דחושבניה תלת מאה ושיתין וארבע d'hushbanei tlat
me'ah v'shitin v'arba
is 364, right? The shin is 300, the nun is 50, the
tet and the hei is another 14, so 364. Meaning he doesn't
have power over us for one day of the year, right, which
is יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Of course now all of a sudden
we're going by the solar year, go figure that out, but okay.
But yeah, but the gematria only works that way. ואמר רבי אמי
בר אבא V'amar Rabbi Ami Bar Abba כתיב אברם ksiv Avram one
verse says Avram וכתיב אברהם u'ksiv Avraham another one says Avraham. It's
not like one verse says it, Avraham's name changed but okay. But
what's the significance of the name change? So בתחילה המליכו הקדוש ברוך
הוא על מאתים וארבעים ושלושה איברים, bit'chila himlicho HaKadosh Baruch Hu al
matayim v'arba'im u'shlosha evarim, now we're all in the gematria world. So
initially God gave Avraham dominion over 243 of his limbs, right?
The idea that a person has 248 limbs. So the gematria of
אברם, Avram, מ, mem, right, the gematria of אברם Avram is 243.
So which were the five he did not have dominion over? ולבסוף
המליכו על מאתים וארבעים ושמונה, u'l'vasof himlicho al matayim v'arba'im u'shmonah, so
the hei gave him complete dominion over all 258 of his
limbs, שתי עיניים shte ayinayim his two eyes ושתי אזניים u'shte oznayim
his two ears וראש הגוויה v'rosh hageviyah
and the tip of his penis which obviously means because of the
ברית מילה. Brit milah, But obviously it means that you know you
cannot control, I mean you could try to stop up your ears
and close your eyes, but sometimes you cannot always control things that
you are seeing and things that you are hearing, and those are
things that can lead you astray. לא תתורו אחרי לבבכם ואחרי עיניכם,
lo tasuru acharei l'vavchem v'acharei eineichem, right? So and obviously the sex
drive is the thing that sort of you know that sort of
drives you to follow those things that you are seeing and hearing
and you know desire. So that's the combination of the things that
sort of create the temptation and then the drive to follow it
and that's what Avraham has control over. And this by the way,
you know in terms of talking about what is the significance of
ברית מילה, Brit milah the meaning of the מצוה, you know רמב"ם
Rambam basically follows this approach that it's to curb the sexual appetite,
you know that the actual ברית מילה, you know part of the
contemporary like you know whole fights around and not just contemporary about
ברית מילה, you know is that it decreases sexual pleasure and therefore
people are saying so it's a terrible thing, you know you shouldn't
do it, you shouldn't do the ברית מילה. And there's I think
debate about this, you know about health benefits and does it decrease
sexual pleasure, increase sexual pleasure etc. But anyway, but רמב"ם Rambam says
yes it does decrease sexual pleasure and that's its purpose because we're
supposed to curb and control our sexual drive. So the גמרא Gemara
here isn't saying that it decreases pleasure, but at least symbolically, you
don't have to say it decreases pleasure to say that symbolically what
it's about is about gaining control and mastery over your drive. drives
and not letting them have control over you. Do anything for eyes
and ears? Right, but I think that the point is that if
you control your, you know, your lust and your drive then you
won't be as led astray by the things that you see and
hear. But you're grouping to put them in the same category. Yeah,
it doesn't... I'm surprised that we don't have some חרדי Haredi interpretation
that says get rid of your eyes and your ears. Well,
I will tell you that about six months ago, right, the חרדים,
Haredim, right, right, right, yes, yes, yes. So, you know, so, I,
you know, like two years ago I wrote this op-ed because about
this thing that was going on in בית שמש Beit Shemesh about
them like attacking this young girl because she was the way she
was dressed and about how, you know, it's really not the obligation
about how women, about how they're dressed, it's really the obligation about
men controlling their looking at women and, you know, and their drives,
and then I was just pleased to see that like not as
a result of this, but like a year later, like a few
months, like maybe six months ago, they came out with these glasses
for חרדי Haredi men that basically distort, that blur, so that they
don't have to see, you know, they see that there is someone
there, but they don't have to actually see it clearly enough that
it can create a יצר הרע Yetzer Hara for them. Well wait,
wait, you have to drive with those glasses?
But just to continue, with the מילה which is done passively to
you so as a result of you being passive you have control
over the things that are passive in your life. Right, you can't
necessarily control... right, the sounds going into your ear and you can't
necessarily control what you see because, you know, your eyes are just
working.
Right,
but I think at the end of the day, you know, you're
master over the passive elements of your life. Yeah, right, but I
think in the end, your, what you do, you are in control
of, you're not in control of things of what happens to you,
you're in control of how you react to them and what do
you do with them, right? So I think that that's the point.
They are just the vehicles by which your inner life is then
affected. Right
and then, right, okay. All right, we got the idea. I think
that the... I'm sorry, go ahead. Okay, let's move on a little.
אמר רמי בר אבא מאי דכתיב? Amar Rami Bar Abba mai d'chtiv?
What's meant by the verse? I mean you can say whatever, it's
gonna be a continuation of the theme, so you'll say it after
this point. מאי דכתיב? Mai d'chtiv? What's meant by the verse? עיר
קטנה, Ir Ketana, this is a little משל mashal in קוהלת. Kohelet.
A small city ואנשים בו מעט, va'anashim bo me'at, so and there
are and there are few people. עיר קטנה זה הגוף, Ir Ketana
zeh haguf, that's the body. ואנשים בה מעט אלו איברים, va'anashim ba
me'at elu evarim, the limbs. ובא אליה מלך גדול וסיבב אותה uva
eleha melech gadol vesivav otah and a king comes and lays siege
to it, surrounds it. זה יצר הרע, zeh yetzer hara,
so this powerful יצר הרע. yetzer hara. You've got your tiny little
body, your weak flesh, and this power your powerful lusts and drives
are trying to take control over it. ובנה עליה מצודים וחרמים uvana
aleha metzudim vecharamim and builds on it like all these instruments of
war, you know, these catapults and whatever. אלו עוונות, elu avonot, so
those are the sins that it lays as traps for you to
fall in, right? So it created all of all of these traps
that your, that so a powerful king has besieged your body and
laid all these pitfalls and traps. ומצא בה איש מסכן וחכם umatza
vah ish misken vechacham
and there was found in there one poor but wise man. זה
יצר טוב, zeh yetzer tov, the small little יצר הטוב, yetzer hatov,
that small little voice of conscience, okay. ומילט את העיר בחכמתו umilat
et ha'ir bechochmato
and he was able to save the city with his wisdom. So
what's the wisdom that saves you from the siege of the יצר
הרע? yetzer hara? זו תשובה ומעשים טובים. zu teshuvah uma'asim tovim.
That is repentance and good deeds. What I think is fascinating is
the word of is תשובה teshuvah because תשובה teshuvah normally sort of
means like, you know, you've already sinned, right? But here it's like
protecting yourself from sin, but maybe it means that the יצר הרע
yetzer hara leads you has to have once you've performed some sins,
right? Those sins meaning when it says that the traps are the
sins, it doesn't just mean that you might sin. Once you've done
some sins you might say like, you know, why should I lead
the good life? I've already sinned, I'm not worthy, you know, I
might as well just sin some more. So the sins that you've
done in the past, right, are traps for you to continue sinning
in the future. And what saves you from that, right? The יצר,
Yetzer, ah, you know, whatever, you've already done it, why, you know,
you're not a צדיק, tzaddik, you can't, you know, you can't live
up to this higher standard. And the יצר Yetzer and the יצר
טוב yetzer tov tells you no, you can do תשובה teshuvah actually,
you can, you know, you can live up to a higher standard.
So I think it's quite fascinating that the עוונות avonot and the
תשובה teshuvah are part of what's potentially not just about the past
but what's leading you astray or protecting you from going astray in
the future as well. Okay, ומעשים טובים. uma'asim tovim. ואדם לא זכר
את האיש, ve'adam lo zachar et ha'ish, so now back to the
פסוק. pasuk. ואדם לא זכר את האיש המסכן ההוא, ve'adam lo zachar
et ha'ish hamisken hahu, nobody remembers that poor man. People know that
the city was saved, but it wasn't through this big act of
valor, right? It was through some wise advice, so nobody remembers that
man. דבשעת יצר הרע לית דמידכר ליה ליצר הטוב. debish'at yetzer hara
leit demidkar leh leyetzer hatov. When your lusts and your drives are
taking control of you, it's hard to remember, you know, about, you
know, to remember that... little voice of conscience and your restraint and
how you were sort of saved from it last time, right? Because
all you ever have are the power of those desires.
Okay, so anyway that's the end of that משל. mashal. I thought
that was a very beautiful משל. mashal. What's it have to do
with taking control over your יצר הרע, yetzer hara, right? And being
able to be in control even though these desires are so powerful,
if you can take control over them. ברית מילה is the foundational
point. Right, although this shifted, and again that's important, like the idea
of תמים, tamim, shifting תמים tamim from physical תמים tamim to תמים
tamim in character, physical אברהם Avraham changing because of the ברית מילה
to control these things to changing because of your יצר הרע, yetzer
hara, because of your developed inner conscience. חכמה תעוז לחכם מעשרה שליטים,
Hachachmah ta'oz l'chacham me'asarah shalitim,
wisdom will become to protect a person or give strength to a
person more than ten shields. חכמה תעוז לחכם, Hachachmah ta'oz l'chacham, wisdom
will give strength to a person, to a wise man. זו תשובה
ומעשים טובים. Zo teshuvah u'ma'asim tovim. So this again is repentance and
good deeds. מעשרה שליטים, Me'asarah shalitim, more than ten shields. שתי עיניים,
Shtei einayim, so these are now ten things that will lead you
astray. שתי עיניים, Shtei einayim, two eyes, ושתי אזניים, u'shtei oznayim, two
ears, ושתי ידיים, u'shtei yadayim, how about the sense of touch, that
will also lead you astray. ושתי רגליים, u'shtei raglayim, your two legs,
they will lead you, they'll actually physically bring you to a place
of sin. וראש הגוויה, V'rosh hagviyah, the tip of the penis, again
your sexual desire. והפה, V'hapeh, and your mouth, right? So things you
talk about and talking לשון הרע lashon hara but just talking about
things will also then whet your appetite.
So all these will lead you astray but your יצר הטוב yetzer
hatov now again, not the physical ברית מילה, but the יצר הטוב,
yetzer hatov, that will protect you. אמר רבי זכריה משום רבי ישמעאל.
Amar Rabi Zechariah mishum Rabi Yishmael. ביקש הקדוש ברוך הוא להוציא כהונה
משם. Bikesh Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'hotzi kehunah miShem. God wanted now, back
to אברהם's Avraham story, God wanted to make שם, Shem, the son
of נח, Noach, into the, his descendants would be the כהנים. kohanim.
It would not be from among בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, but the
כהנים kohanim in the world would be the descendants of שם. Shem.
שנאמר, והוא כהן לאל עליון. ve'hu kohen l'El elyon.
מלכי צדק מלך שלם, Malki-Tzedek Melech Shalem, who is understood by חז״ל
Chazal to be שם, Shem, the son of נח, Noach, says he
was a כהן kohen to the Most High God.
So that he would have been the כהן kohen for all future
generations, his descendants. כיוון שהקדים ברכת אברהם לברכת המקום. Keivan she'hikdim birkat
Avraham l'birkat HaMakom.
By the way, you have to think about for a moment the
power of that idea, that it would actually say not like בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael are chosen and among בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael the
כהנים kohanim are chosen, which is our way of thinking about it,
but actually, there could have been the category of כהנים kohanim which
would have been the non-Jews in the world, not Jews, and they
would have been in this special hierarchy and category of כהנים kohanim
higher in some ways, serving in the Temple as opposed to בני
ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So a sort of nice, strikes a nice universalist
type of an idea, at least in theory, right?
But כיוון שהקדים ברכת אברהם לברכת המקום, keivan she'hikdim birkat Avraham l'birkat
HaMakom, but when he blessed אברהם Avraham, before he blessed God, הוציאה
מאברהם, hotzi'ah me'Avraham, so God then said, okay, now the כהנים kohanim
are coming from אברהם, Avraham you lost your shot. שנאמר ויברכהו ויאמר,
Shenemar v'yevarchehu v'yomar, he blessed him and he said, ברוך אברהם לאל
עליון, Baruch Avraham l'El elyon, blessed be אברהם Avraham to the Most
High God, קונה שמים וארץ, koneh shamayim va'aretz, owner or creator is
what קונה koneh can mean of heaven and earth. וברוך אל עליון,
u'varuch El elyon, and blessed be the Most High God. אמר לו
אברהם, Amar lo Avraham, אברהם Avraham said to him, וכי מקדימין ברכת
עבד לברכת קונו? ve'chi makdimin birkat eved l'birkat kono? Do you give
the blessing of the slave before the ברכה bracha of his owner?
Or some have ברכת רבו, birkat rabo, of his master. מיד ניתנה
לאברהם. Miyad nitnah l'Avraham.
So then אברהם Avraham. got the כהנים kohanim coming from him. שנאמר
נאום ה׳ לאדוני. Shenemar neum Hashem l'adoni.
God said to my master, this is דוד David talking and אדוני
adoni in this context means אברהם. שב לימיני, Shev l'ymini, sit at
my right hand, עד אשית אויביך הדום לרגליך, ad ashit oyvecha hadom
l'raglecha, until I make your enemies your footstool. ובתר כתיב, U'vatar ktiv,
and then afterwards it says, נשבע ה׳ ולא ינחם, nishba Hashem v'lo
yinachem, God has sworn and he will not renege, אתה כהן לעולם
על דברתי מלכי צדק. atah kohen l'olam al dibrati Malki-Tzedek.
You are the priest forever because I have spoken regarding מלכי צדק.
Malki-Tzedek. What does that mean, על דברתי מלכי צדק, al dibrati Malki-Tzedek,
very bizarre פסוק? pasuk? So the גמרא Gemara says, על דיבורו של
מלכי צדק, al diburo shel Malki-Tzedek, because of what מלכי צדק Malki-Tzedek
spoke, because of how he misspoke, you now are going to be
the כהן. kohen. והיינו דכתיב, V'haynu d'chtiv, והוא כהן לאל עליון. ve'hu
kohen l'El elyon.
He was a כהן kohen for אל עליון, El elyon, הוא כהן,
hu kohen, he was a כהן kohen ואין זרעו כהן, ve'ein zaro
kohen, but not his future descendants. So again, what really determined, notice
by the way the amazing thing here at the end. All along
we were dealing with this tension between the physical reality, the ברית
מילה, and the
more character issue. Are you תמים tamim because of the ברית, are
you תמים tamim because you're a character? Does the ברית מילה give
you control over your desires, or does your יצר טוב yetzer tov
give you control over your desires? Like this all in מסכת נדרים,
Masechet Nedarim, which is about words, and what do we find out
at the end? What in the end determined who was going to
be the כהן? kohen? The words, right? How were the words used
properly or the words not used properly? So again, I think it's
fascinating to sort of the dialectic here between the power of words.
the physical realities in which we live and the words that shape
our realities. Yeah, I'd like to suggest that this entire סוגיא sugya
in contemporary terms, in a way acknowledges what we might call the
dispute or tension between behaviorist or psychodynamic orientation. How does
a person change or transform? You focus on the behavior, on the
physical dimension of the person, or on the person's inner self. Oh,
very nice.
The character. Those are two really major. שכח שכח. shkoach shkoach. Very,
very nice. Okay, let's start the next פרק. הנודר מן המאכל. ha'noder
min ha'ma'achal. So that's the end of ארבעה נדרים. arba'ah nedarim. Now
this next פרק as I said is not just a next פרק,
I mean it is, but you'll see a major shift. Like the
first three פרקים are about what are the words, what are the
thoughts you need to create a נדר, neder, what's the population included
in your נדר, neder, who do you mean when you say these
types of people and so on. This says you've got your נדר.
neder. This loaf of bread is אסור assur to Michael. I was
very clear, no question the נדר neder is חל. chal. What does
it mean that it's אסור assur to him? What's included in the—what
is the scope of how he can and can't use it? Okay,
so it's a very different type of a topic. אין בין המודר
הנאה מחבירו למודר הימנו מאכל. ein bein ha'mudar hana'ah me'chavero l'mudar heimenu
ma'achal. There's no difference between somebody that is, you know, that is
avowed from getting pleasure from his friend to somebody that is avowed
from getting from him, sort of food or like the pleasure of
food, as opposed to generically you can't get pleasure. If I say
to Michael, you know, you can't get pleasure from me, קונם konam
that I am forbidden to you, or קונם הנאת מאכל אסורה עליך,
konam hana'at ma'achal asurah alecha, so you think there's a huge difference.
There's a million types of benefits that are not related to food.
Right. So the גמרא is going to understand—well, let's take a look
at what the משנה says. The only difference is אלא דריסת הרגל.
ela drisat ha'regel. That if you can't get any benefit from me,
then you can't cut through my yard. But if you can't get
food benefit, you can cut through my yard. והכלים שאין עושים בהם
אוכל נפש, ve'ha'keilim she'ein osim bahem ochel nefesh, vessels that are not
used for food purposes. Okay, now why—meaning so like—now that's crazy. Like
why can I go ahead and lend Michael my rake?
Like why can I—excuse me—you know, why are those the only differences?
I mean there's plenty of things that are not in those categories
that are also not food benefits. So what the גמרא is going
to say is that when I say you can't get food benefit,
what it's—how it's going to be—what I said or how it'll be
interpreted to mean is you can't get any benefit that can translate
into food. So any benefit I give Michael that's worth any money—well,
anything that's worth any money could translate into food. If it's worth
a penny, he could go to the store and buy a piece
of gum. You know, anything can—it can translate. So the only benefit
that won't translate into food is benefit that is not worth money,
that nobody would pay for. So what would nobody pay for? Well,
cutting across my yard is a type of a thing which, you
know, which is not something that people—I could charge for it, but
normally people—sure, no problem, you can cut across my yard. It's normally
not a type of thing that anyone—so it's not a benefit that
has a dollar—that has a dollar value attached to it. Okay, but
what about כלים? keilim? What about כלים? keilim? So the גמרא is
going to say that כלים keilim that are—I would rent, like if
I would normally rent my rake to people, then he can't borrow
my rake. But if I normally just, sure, I'll lend my rake
to people who ask for it, I'm a nice guy, then that's
not a benefit that could translate into money. משל, mashal, well, the
types of things that people normally don't charge for, that normally people
wouldn't pay for. Okay, so that—I don't know why it's interpreted that
way, it might be that you framed it particularly that way. Let's
just finish reading the משנה, we'll pick up with this tomorrow. Okay.
אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, המדיר. ha'madir.
So but even if I normally don't charge when I lend out
my—my rolling pin, that I can't lend him. Because even though that's
not—doesn't translate into money, that is food-related. Okay. So המודר מאכל מחבירו,
ha'mudar ma'achal me'chavero,
if you're not allowed to get any food benefit from me, לא
ישאילנו נפה וכברה וריחיים. lo yash'ilenu nafah u'chevarah ve'reichayim.
You can't lend the person a sieve and a כברה kevarah is
another type of a sieve and a colander and a millstone, ותנור
ve'tanur and an oven. Because all those types of things, even if
I would normally lend them to people without charging, those obviously will
translate into a food benefit. אבל משאיל לו חלוק וטבעת וטלית ועגילים.
aval mash'il lo chaluk ve'tabaat ve'talit ve'agilim. I can lend him my
shirt and a ring and a cloak and earrings or whatever, nose
ring. So again, interestingly, we are translating when you say you can't
get food benefit, means A, literally benefit that relates to food, and
B, benefit that is—has a dollar value associated with it that could
translate into food. And that's why it's a much more broader scope
than we would normally expect. And the only things that are not
included are things that normally nobody would pay for. Okay, so we'll—כלים
keilim could mean clothing. What? Oh,
could be. Could be, yes. Okay, we will see this more tomorrow.